to pay for the sin of humanity.
I'm thankful that he was buried,
but he rose conquering sin, death, and the grave.
He is alive forevermore.
And as they said, shout and proclaim
that he's coming back, amen.
And if you're saved this morning,
you've trusted Jesus Christ as your personal savior.
He's coming back for you.
Listen for the trumpet, Jesus is coming, amen.
And we are thankful and we are blessed.
Thank you for singing this morning.
And I've already sensed
that we're worshiping the Lord today, amen.
He is worthy of our worship.
Luke 19 in your Bibles this morning,
Luke chapter number 19,
and I'm gonna read the first 10 verses of Scripture
as we get into the message this morning.
It's a familiar passage of Scripture.
And I hope that this morning the Lord will help us
as we look at this portion of Scripture,
encourage us and challenge us to be doers of the word
and not hearers only.
In Luke 19 in verse number one,
the Bible says,
and Jesus entered and passed through Jericho.
Behold, there was a man named Zacchaeus,
which was the chief among the publicans and he was rich.
And he sought to see Jesus who he was
and could not for the press
because he was little of stature.
And he ran before and climbed up into a sycamore tree
to see him for he was to pass that way.
And when Jesus came to the place,
he looked up and saw him and said unto him,
Zacchaeus, make haste and come down
for today I must abide at thy house.
And he made haste and came down and received him joyfully.
When they saw it,
they all murmured saying that he was gone
to be guest with a man that is a sinner.
And Zacchaeus stood and said unto the Lord,
behold, Lord, the half of my goods I give to the poor.
And if I've taken anything from any man
by false accusation, I restore him fourfold.
And Jesus said unto him, notice in verse nine,
this day is salvation come to this house
for as much as he also is a son of Abraham,
for the son of man has come to seek and to save
that which was lost.
As we look at this portion of scripture,
I've titled the message from verse number nine,
this day is salvation come to this house.
As we get to look at this portion of scripture,
I'm reminded that tomorrow personally will be 29 years
since I trusted Jesus Christ as my personal savior.
And I'm so thankful that on that particular day
that the Holy Spirit of God convinced me
of my need for the Savior,
the only Savior, the Lord Jesus Christ.
And it was not much to convince me that I was guilty,
that I was a sinner.
The problem was that I didn't know
what was going to happen when I died as a sinner.
I had this idea that I could be a good enough person
and maybe at the end of the whole situation,
there'd be this giant scale and it would determine
whether I'd have entrance to or not to heaven.
If someone were to ask me, if you were to die today,
are you sure that heaven is your home?
My answer at that point would have been, I hope so.
And I had zero assurance, it was just simply a hope,
a wishful thinking that that would be the case.
However, 29 years ago tomorrow,
I got on my knees in the living room of our house
in Southern California,
and I recognized that I was a sinner
and Jesus was the only Savior.
And I prayed and asked him to be my personal Savior.
And on that day, he saved me.
And what a joy and what a blessing.
And from that day to this day,
if someone were to ask me,
are you sure that heaven is your home?
I could answer, absolutely,
with 100% confidence and assurance
because it's not based upon what I did,
but it's based upon what Jesus Christ did
on the cross of Calvary,
his death, burial, and glorious resurrection.
And I would say it this way,
just as we've seen in Luke chapter 19,
it was a personal decision on a particular day.
The decision was mine personally, it was not my dad's.
He was there in the room with me,
but it wasn't his decision, it was my decision.
And it was on a particular day.
Jesus said to Nicodemus in John chapter number three,
marvel not that I say unto thee, ye must be born again.
And on that day, I'm so thankful that I was born again.
I was saved by the grace of God.
As we look at this familiar portion of scripture
in Luke chapter 19,
we see this interaction between the Lord Jesus Christ
and Zacchaeus.
I said that it was a familiar passage of scripture
for many of us,
and you've heard perhaps this portion of scripture
at some point.
Verse number 10 is an oft quoted verse
that reveals to us and reminds us
of the singular purpose
of the coming of the Lord Jesus Christ.
And that is to seek and to save that which was lost.
And I'm so thankful that he is a seeking savior.
And we find here this morning
that oftentimes even in Sunday school classes
or in junior church classes
or vacation Bible schools
that we'll sing that song
about Zacchaeus was a wee little man
and a wee little man was he.
And some of you know that song
and I'm not gonna sing it for you this morning.
We've already had some great music
and I don't wanna spoil that.
But the reality is that we might be familiar
because of knowing some of those things.
But as we dig in here to this portion of scripture,
I want you to consider three things as we look here.
Number one, if you're taking notes,
I want you to notice the condition of Zacchaeus.
The condition of Zacchaeus.
We see that he's an individual
and we find that as you study
through this portion of scripture
that the Bible tells us
that there were a great number of people.
He says in verse number three,
he could not for the press
because he was little of stature.
And so therefore he climbed up into that sycamore tree.
There's a number of people there,
but it's always amazing to me
that as you study the scriptures
and especially in the gospel records,
the interactions of the Lord Jesus Christ,
you find that though there's multitudes of people,
oftentimes the focus of scripture is on an individual.
There were multitudes, but there's a certain leper.
There's a press of people,
but Zacchaeus is the one that zeroed in on here.
We find that as you look at Mark chapter number two,
that there's so many people
that they can't even get the man into the door,
into the presence of Jesus.
But yet the Bible tells us
that they let him down through a roof tile
and that man that was born of four.
And over and over you find that we serve a God
who is a God who loves the entire world,
but he's interested in the individuals.
I'm so thankful that the Bible teaches us
that God so loved the world.
I'm thankful for that,
but I'm reminded like what the songwriters said,
wonderful things in the Bible I see,
but this is the dearest that Jesus loves me.
Praise the Lord that he is a personal God
and he's a personal savior.
And we see the condition of this man, Zacchaeus.
Notice with me in verse number two,
we find the condition of this man
and we first think about and notice his position.
The Bible says in verse number two,
and behold, there was a man named Zacchaeus.
Notice what the Bible says,
which was the chief among the publicans.
And so it's a noticed with regard
to the position of this man
that he's the chief among the publicans.
It doesn't just tell us that he was a publican,
but he's chief among the publicans.
Can I tell you this morning that there are some in life
that are concerned primarily
with what their position in life is.
They are always seeking after a title and a position
and that's what they find some level of satisfaction
and some level of contentment in is that position.
And we find here as we look at Luke chapter 19,
that this man Zacchaeus had position.
He was chief among the publicans.
Not only did he have position,
but we see that he had possessions.
The end of the verse in verse number two says,
and he was rich.
He was rich.
You know, there's a lot of people
that are seeking possessions, wealth and rich and riches.
How much can I get?
How much can I obtain?
And we find that many have position
and many have possessions.
And this man Zacchaeus, as you study Luke chapter 19
and you consider the condition of this man,
it seems like from the outside, if you will,
that he's got everything
that an individual could possibly want.
I mean, he's got the position.
He has the possessions.
And yet we find that this man,
though he was chief among the publicans,
though he was rich,
I would submit to you this morning that he was empty.
He was empty.
Can I tell you this morning that you and I
have been created by the omnipotent, omniscient God
who loves us and he created us
to have this hole in our souls and our lives
filled only by him.
There is no position,
there is no possession that can bring you satisfaction
like the Lord Jesus Christ can bring
in the life of an individual.
There is a God-shaped hole in every single person
that's ever been created
and man tries to fill it with possession.
position and possession, but they find themselves lacking.
They find themselves empty.
Look at it, the Bible says that he sought
to see Jesus, who he was.
See this man who, from the outward,
from maybe the friends and those
that he would rub shoulders with,
that seemed like he had it all together.
He had the position, he had the possessions,
but yet the Bible says that he sought.
See he was seeking.
Why, because he wasn't filled.
He wasn't satisfied.
There was something lacking.
And I would submit to you that you could read accounts
of individuals that have written their own testimonies
at the end of life, and they've been asked questions
and interviewed about various things,
and they say this, that I'll tell you one thing,
that riches, they just don't satisfy.
I'll tell you this, the position, it just doesn't satisfy.
It's temporary.
I was reminded even the other day on Thursday,
I believe it was, where the Bible tells us
in the book of Proverbs that riches make wings
and they fly away, and Brianna had asked
for a little cash for something,
and I went to stick it under her door at the house,
but the air conditioning was on,
and as soon as I stuck it under the door,
that money went flying out of the door.
And I thought it was kind of comical,
but it reminded me, Holly was standing right next to me,
and I said, well, like Proverbs said,
riches make wings and they fly away, you know?
But the reality is that those things are temporary.
They're just temporary.
And this man, he was empty.
There was something missing.
Though at the end of the day, he could go home,
or if we could think about it in today's kind of economy
and in our culture, he could walk into the corner office,
so to speak, with the name plaque on the door,
and really, man, he's chief among the publicans,
and he can walk in and he has that position,
and he could buy what he wanted.
He had the riches, but he's lacking.
Something was missing.
We find that in verse number eight of our,
or sorry, verse number seven of our text of Scripture,
when we consider the condition of this man, Zacchaeus,
notice what the Bible says in verse number seven.
It says, and when they saw it,
now, to understand the context of what's going on,
remember, there was a great host of people,
as we read in verse number three,
that he could not get to where Jesus was
because of the press,
because of the group of people that were there.
The Bible says that when they saw it,
those that were gathered, they all murmured.
And notice what they said.
They said that he, that would be Jesus,
was gone to be guest with a man that is a sinner.
The condition of this man is clearly given to us
in verse number seven, that this man was a sinner.
But can I tell you that that's a universal condition
of all humanity?
The Bible tells us in Romans chapter number three,
that all have sinned and come short of the glory of God.
The Bible tells us that we are all sinners,
and we understand that there is a problem.
Again, it's a universal condition.
The only individual that's ever walked
upon the face of the earth without sin
is the Lord Jesus Christ, God in flesh.
And he died for us, he who knew no sin,
he took our place, but we understand that this man,
and the statement is so interesting,
that these that were gathered,
that they would say of this man, Zacchaeus,
he's a sinner.
Guess what?
They were sinners, right?
They're looking at this man and looking at his condition
and saying, oh, he's a sinner.
We're all sinners.
Here's the question is whether we're a sinner
that's been saved by the grace of God, amen?
And the moment I got saved, I didn't stop sinning.
I should sin less and less as I walk
with the Lord Jesus Christ,
but this flesh was not eradicated,
and your flesh was not eradicated
at the moment that you trusted Jesus Christ
as your personal savior.
And we find that those that were throwing
this statement of he is a sinner,
I can't believe that Jesus went to be guest
with a man that's a sinner.
They themselves are sinners.
So we understand this morning the condition of Zacchaeus.
This morning, I believe that each of us can relate
to the condition of Zacchaeus,
and we can understand in the world in which we live in,
and we can find that whether we had possession or position,
whether those things were true,
we would find that before we were saved,
that there was this thing that something was missing.
There was some emptiness.
It was a recognition that we're sinners.
This morning, I'm thankful to be saved,
and I've been saved from the penalty of sin,
but we understand the condition and we can relate.
As we look at the text,
we not only notice the condition of Zacchaeus,
but I want you to notice number two,
the compassion of Jesus.
I'm so thankful this morning that we have a savior
that is compassionate.
that is moved with compassion.
And as we look at the passage here that is before us,
we find it quite interesting that in verse number one,
you notice some purpose with regard to the movement
of the Lord Jesus Christ.
It says in Luke 19 in verse number one,
and Jesus entered and passed through Jericho.
It reminds me of what we read in John chapter number four,
when the Bible says that Jesus said
that he must needs go through Samaria.
And we understand that Jericho is a different region
than Samaria, but understand that here in Jericho
is the Bible tells us in verse number one,
that Jesus not only entered into,
but it said that he passed through Jericho.
Everything that our Lord does is on purpose and with purpose.
As we begin reading in verse number one,
and you get down to verse number three,
and you begin to see about Zacchaeus, how he was seeking,
I would say to you that Jesus was seeking Zacchaeus
long before Zacchaeus was seeking Jesus.
And I'm so thankful for the way in which Zacchaeus,
how did he know?
How did he hear about Jesus?
The fame was going abroad of the work
of the Lord Jesus Christ.
And this man Zacchaeus heard and he's coming,
but understand that Jesus had this divine appointment.
And he specifically, and on purpose,
he entered and he passed through Jericho.
We find that as you would begin to understand
the compassion of Jesus and recognize the purpose,
but we also see the fact that he's personal.
I mentioned this already a moment ago,
but I want you to specifically look at verse number five
with me, and the Bible says this in verse number five,
and when Jesus came, notice what it says to the place.
Now think about it again, if I could help us
have this sanctified imagination to see what's taking place,
there's a multitude of people.
And Jesus is passing through,
you've been in a crowd of people before
and you understand the masses and just kind of passing
and we find that this man Zacchaeus, he's up in a tree.
And he's there because he's desiring to see
the Lord Jesus Christ.
And it tells us that in verse number four,
that he ran before, and so there's so many people,
they're pressed, he couldn't get to where Jesus was,
so he ran ahead, he gets up into this tree
so that he could see the Lord as he passed by.
Now think about that with me.
His longing and desire was to see,
according to verse number three,
he sought to see Jesus, who he was.
And we find that in verse number four,
that Jesus was to pass that way and he's up in a tree
and having this interest.
Now recognize with me this morning
that he would not know who he was
by simply seeing him pass by.
But it says in verse number five,
that when Jesus came to the place,
he looked up and he saw him and said unto him.
Now again, there's a lot of people there,
but Jesus personally starts dealing with Zacchaeus.
The Bible says this, Zacchaeus,
this is what Jesus says to Zacchaeus,
make haste and come down.
For today, do you notice that word, I must?
I must abide at thy house.
Isn't that awesome?
I mean, to think about the compassion
of the Lord Jesus Christ that he looked at,
saw, and then spoke to Zacchaeus,
and he told Zacchaeus that to make haste,
I mean, do not delay, there was urgency,
make haste, come down, for today I must abide at thy house.
And I'm so thankful for the response in verse number six
that Zacchaeus didn't say, I'm too busy,
maybe some other time.
I'm just, no, he made haste and he came down, amen?
And praise the Lord for that.
I preached last week from Mark chapter number six,
that he saw them, and I said this
as we looked at the text of scripture,
that Jesus knew exactly where the disciples were
in the midst of that sea, and it tells us
that he walked on that water
and he would have passed them by.
But John told us that he records for us
that they willingly received him into the ship
and how that made all the difference.
Zacchaeus responded well to the invitation
that was given in verse seven.
I want you to notice that this really reveals to us
the compassion of Jesus with working with Zacchaeus here
in Luke chapter 19 reveals to us the primary purpose
that is revealed in verse number 10 to the work
and ministry of the Lord Jesus Christ.
For the Son of Man has come to seek and to save
that which was lost.
I'm thankful that He's a seeking Savior.
I'm thankful that on August 31st, 1997
that He found me and He saved me.
And I'm thankful for many of you that have shared
your personal testimony of salvation with me
that you were saved by the grace of God.
This morning, if you're not saved, if you do not have assurance
that heaven is your home, can I tell you that God loves you?
That Jesus died for you, that He was buried and He rose again.
We've been singing about it this morning.
We've had the opportunity to look here this morning
at this portion of scripture to see the compassion
of the Lord Jesus Christ.
Now, understand as Jesus would go and enter
into the home of Zacchaeus, the Bible says
that Zacchaeus received Him joyfully.
And the Bible doesn't give us all of the details
with regard to the interaction that Zacchaeus
had with Jesus in His house.
It's not recorded for us, but can I tell you
that Zacchaeus was seeking, according to verse number three,
to see Jesus in the notice who He was.
He wasn't just seeking Jesus to find out what He could do.
Think about that for a moment.
Herod was gonna seek Jesus for a long time,
wanted to see Him, why?
Because he heard about the miracles, what He could do.
In John chapter number six, Jesus says,
hey, you're not here because you really desire Me,
you're here because you ate the bread.
What He could do.
Can I tell you this morning, there's some people
that wanna seek Jesus so that they can find out
what Jesus can do for them or what He can do.
But the real question is, who is He?
Who is He?
See, Zacchaeus wasn't so much interested
in seeing some miracle.
Now, he did see a miracle, we'll see it in just a moment.
But he was interested, who is He?
It reminds me of what Jesus said
in Matthew chapter number 16
when He's speaking to His disciples.
Whom do men say that I am?
Who is Jesus?
And in that day, in the first century,
there were some that said, well, it's John the Baptist,
Jeremiah, one of the prophets.
And then Jesus says, but whom say ye that I am?
And some of you are familiar with the passage
and Peter stands up and he says,
thou art the Christ, the Son of the living God.
Praise God for that proclamation.
And we find this morning that the question
still remains in 2026, who is Jesus?
Who is He?
He is God in flesh.
He is the Messiah.
He is the promised one.
We find that He is the Redeemer,
the Savior of the world.
At this point in Luke chapter 19,
He's not yet gone to the cross of Calvary,
but soon He would.
And we know that if you read John 17
that it was so absolutely certain
that Jesus would go and fulfill what He came to do
that He could speak of the event being finished
though He had not even gone to the cross yet.
And we find the compassion
that Jesus stops at that tree
and He looks up and He says,
Make haste, come down.
I must abide at thy house today.
And we begin to look at this portion of Scripture
and we begin to see this personal interaction
between the Lord Jesus Christ, God in flesh,
and Zacchaeus and we rejoice
in understanding at this point
all that has transpired
and that Jesus would reveal Himself.
Listen, I want you to know this morning,
I've said this to so many people over the years,
if you want to know truth, God will reveal truth to you.
He is truth.
Jesus said, I am the way, the truth, and the life.
No man cometh unto the Father but by me.
And we find that the Lord Jesus Christ,
He's given to us a Bible.
We have the Scriptures that reveal to us
who He is and what He has done.
And we find that He wants people, humanity, to know truth.
See, because He's compassionate, because He's love,
we've been dealing with this on Wednesday evenings
looking through the book of 2 John.
God is love.
God is truth.
Because God is love, God gave us truth.
Because He loves us, He wants us to know the truth.
And the truth is that all the way back in the beginning
that God made humanity.
And when He made Adam and He made Eve,
He made them perfect.
But the truth is that they sinned.
And when they sinned, the Bible tells us that death
entered into the world.
The Bible says that we've all sinned.
I believe this morning that every single one of us,
including Zacchaeus, would be able to acknowledge
that we're sinners.
And it's all because of what happened all the way back in the garden.
When Adam and Eve partook of the forbidden fruit,
and they took part and their eyes were opened.
And you know what they tried to do?
They tried to cover their nakedness.
And they tried to, by the works of their own hands,
they tried to cover their nakedness.
Listen, that's what so many people are trying to do today
with regard to covering their sin.
They're trying to do good things.
I don't remember which one sang the part of the song
this morning from the Trejos, but about their good works.
Listen, it never could work.
For by grace are you saved through faith,
and that not of yourselves is the gift of God,
not of works lest any man should boast.
And so we find this morning that those works of their hands
that they sought to try to cover their nakedness,
their shame because of their sin,
was insufficient.
So what did God do?
Well, God came to where they were and he met their need.
An animal was sacrificed, was slain,
and through that blood was shed,
but a coat of skin was provided to cover.
And that coat of skin was provided to cover,
but the significance is in the blood that was shed.
And that blood that was shed was a prophetical truth
with regard to the Lord Jesus Christ,
who is, according to what Peter would later tell us,
the Lamb of God that was slain
before the foundation of the world.
And we find that it's a picture,
a prophetic picture of the Lord Jesus Christ,
who is our Passover, who would come
and shed his precious blood.
And so I believe that just as you would read in a few chapters
in Luke chapter number 24,
that as Jesus, after his resurrection,
is walking there and there's those two disciples
that are walking on the road back to Emmaus
and they're discouraged and downhearted
and they have all of these difficulties
because of all that had transpired.
And the Bible tells us that Jesus,
according to verse 27 of Luke 24,
beginning at Moses and all the prophets,
he expounded unto them in all the scriptures
the things concerning himself.
I think Zacchaeus got a little bit of that in Luke 19.
I think Jesus, again, he wants us to know who he is.
He's given us a book.
The Bible tells us that the heavens declare the glory of God.
The firmament showeth forth his handiwork.
You know, it's a difficult thing
when somebody says they're an atheist
because there's so much evidence for God.
So much evidence.
In fact, someone wrote a book, Frank Turek,
that takes more faith to be an atheist.
And the reality is that this morning,
God has given us the witness of creation.
He's given us the witness of his word
because he wants us to know the truth.
We see the condition of Zacchaeus.
We see the compassion of Jesus.
But I want you to notice number three this morning,
the conversion of Zacchaeus,
the conversion of Zacchaeus.
I believe that as you look back in Luke 19
and we look at verses eight and nine,
you see the conversion of this man, Zacchaeus,
and he found out exactly who Jesus is.
He found out, he sought to see Jesus,
who he was in verse number three.
And I believe that he discovered exactly who Jesus is,
that Jesus spoke to him and gave him truth
and answered those questions.
And we find that Zacchaeus now would take
and trust the Lord Jesus Christ as his personal savior.
Now, let me try to help you with verse number eight
because there's some that would misunderstand
and take out of context the truth of verse number eight.
But I want you to see in verse number eight
that after Jesus and Zacchaeus had this meeting in his house,
that in verse number eight, Zacchaeus stood
and said unto the Lord, notice what he says,
behold, and then it says, Lord.
So recognize with me immediately
that Zacchaeus is calling him Lord.
In the beginning of the text in verse number three,
it says,
He says that he sought to see Jesus, who he was.
So he didn't know, Zacchaeus at the beginning of the interaction didn't know who Jesus is,
but after the meeting in the house, after the revelation, after Jesus expounded to Zacchaeus,
whatever the content was that he expounded, that Zacchaeus says, Lord.
That's a proper term to refer to the Lord Jesus Christ.
And we find that the Bible tells us, and you don't need to turn there, but over in the
book of Philippians, I'm going to just read for you very quickly a portion of scripture.
Then in the book of Philippians in chapter number two and verse number eight, well, I'm
going to start in verse number five.
It says, let this mind be in you, which was also in Christ Jesus, who being in the form
of God, thought it not robbery to be equal with God, but made himself of no reputation
and took upon him the form of a servant was made in the likeness of men and being found
in fashion as a man, he humbled himself and became obedient unto death, even the death
of the cross.
Wherefore, verse nine says, God also hath highly exalted him and given him a name, which
is above every name, that in the name of Jesus, notice what the Bible says, every knee,
not most, every knee should bow of things in heaven and things in earth and things under
the earth.
And that every tongue, notice what it says, every tongue should confess that Jesus Christ
is Lord.
Is that what it says in your Bible?
To the glory of God the Father.
Do you notice what Zacchaeus did?
Who is he?
Who is Jesus?
He'd heard about Jesus.
Who is this man from Galilee?
Who is he?
Well, he's the Lord.
He's God in flesh.
And so we find that by the time he comes out in verse number eight, that he says, behold,
Lord, listen, every knee, we just read it for you from Philippians chapter number two,
every knee is going to bow and every tongue is going to confess that Jesus Christ is Lord.
The question is this, when?
It's not a question of if, it's a question of when.
Because the Bible plainly says that every knee will bow and every tongue will confess.
So if it's not a question of if, it's a question of when.
For me, when did I make that confession?
When did I recognize that?
It was 29 years ago tomorrow.
It was a personal decision on a particular day.
And I would ask you this morning, and I would tell you, I would ask you this, when?
When have you confessed that Jesus Christ is Lord?
When have you trusted Jesus as your personal Savior?
It's not a question of if, it's a question of when.
And I would submit to you this morning that when makes all the difference.
When makes all the difference.
See, if you do it on this side of eternity, what do I mean by that?
Well, before we take our final breath.
As it is appointed unto man once to die, after this the judgment.
I'm going to die one day, and so are you.
I remember telling a man, it was several years ago now, he was at the bank.
He looked very miserable as he walked in.
It was just me and him and a couple of the tellers.
And I saw him walk in.
He looked like a, he was just a grumpy old guy.
And I said, hey, how are you?
One of those kind of deals.
You've met people like that before?
And he said, how are you?
I said, absolutely wonderful.
And he looked at me and he said, you're a liar.
You're lying.
I said, what do you mean I'm lying?
He said, no one's absolutely wonderful.
I said, man, I'm going to heaven when I die.
And then he said this, you're dying?
I was like, well, as far as I know, I'm not dying today.
But I am going to die one day.
But I know I'm going to heaven.
That can make us absolutely wonderful, amen?
Because I know for sure that when I die,
I'm going to go to heaven.
And so when makes all the difference?
Because if you do it on this side of eternity,
then you'll spend forever in heaven with Jesus.
The Bible says to be absent from the body
is to be present with the Lord.
But see, after we take our final breath here on earth,
there's no more opportunity
to change our eternal destination.
The Bible says that those that die without Christ
will spend eternity in the lake of fire.
That's what the Bible says.
Revelation chapter 20.
You can read verses 14 and 15.
And you can see that the Bible plainly teaches
that those that die without the Lord Jesus Christ,
their personal savior,
they will spend eternity in the lake of fire.
But before they're cast into the lake of fire,
there's a judgment that's called
the great white throne judgment.
And I believe that it's at that judgment
that every knee is going to bow
and every tongue is going to confess
that Jesus Christ is Lord to the glory of the Father.
But at that moment, though they confess,
that's the when, it's too late
to change their eternal destiny.
I hope that makes sense for you this morning.
It's not a question of if, it's a question of when,
and when makes all the difference.
And so we find that Zacchaeus says, Lord.
Then notice what he says.
The half of my goods I give to the poor.
And if I have taken anything from any man
by false accusation, I restore him fourfold.
Now I would describe verse number eight this way.
This is the evidence of his conversion.
This is not the reason for his conversion, okay?
For by grace are you saved through faith, right?
Not of yourselves, it tells us it's not of works
lest any man should boast.
We understand that the Bible plainly teaches us
throughout the scriptures that the gift of God
is eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord.
It's not something that I can earn.
It's not something I can pay for.
It's not even really something that I deserve.
But because God loved me, he offers to me.
Because God loves you, he offers to you
the gift of eternal life.
And we find here that verse number eight
would be the evidence of Zacchaeus' conversion.
The fact that he, as we would consider the truth
of 2 Corinthians 5, 17, that the Bible says,
therefore if any man be in Christ, he is a new creature.
Old things are passed away, behold,
all things are become new.
And so because of this miraculous conversion,
I said that he was seeking who he was, who Jesus was.
He wasn't just seeking to see Jesus do some miracle,
but he was the personal recipient
of the greatest of all miracles,
and that's the conversion of a soul.
And I'm so thankful this morning that Zacchaeus,
again, verse eight is the evidence,
because he was a new creature,
because he was saved by the grace of God,
he was made alive, he says, I'm going to live differently.
We sing the song, we talk about singing it with children,
and we ought to sing it with adults as well.
There's been a great change since I've been born again.
The things I used to do, I don't do them anymore, amen?
The places I used to go, I don't go there anymore.
The things I used to say, the things I used to wash,
go on and on and on, as many verses as you want
to that glorious song, why?
Because there's been a great change
since I've been born again.
And I hope this morning that as you look at your life
and you examine your life, you say,
hey, is there evidence of conversion?
You can't be saved by giving money to the poor.
You can't be saved by restoring to those that you defrauded.
It's not how salvation comes.
By the way, if it could come that way,
Jesus would not have had to die.
If you could get to heaven by being a good person,
if I could get to heaven by being a good person,
Jesus would not have had to die
the horrific death that he did.
Paul said it this way, I do not frustrate the grace of God,
for if righteousness come by the law,
then Christ is dead in vain.
But the law that Paul would continue to speak of
in the book of Galatians, the law could not bring life.
It didn't have the ability to bring life.
You know what the law does?
It condemns.
The law condemns.
It tells us that we're a sinner.
The Bible tells us in the book of Galatians
it's a schoolmaster.
And what that teaches us is that it cannot,
the law cannot give life,
but what it does is it leads us
to the only one that can, Jesus Christ.
And what a blessing.
And so we see the evidence of his conversion
in verse number eight,
but then I want you to notice in verse number nine,
the words of the Lord Jesus Christ.
And I would say it this way,
it's the confirmation of his conversion.
The Lord Jesus Christ is gonna confirm
that this man, Zacchaeus, was saved,
that he was converted.
The Bible says in verse number nine,
and Jesus said unto him,
this day is salvation come to this house,
for so much as he also is a son of Abraham.
I've said it a couple of times already this morning,
but I'm gonna say it again.
When you read verse number nine,
it says this day, that's a particular day.
And it says, is salvation come to this house?
That's a personal decision.
And so it's a personal decision.
on a particular day.
Paul writes about his kinsmen, his brethren,
according to the flesh, the Jewish people,
and he writes in Romans 9 and Romans chapter number 10
that he had great heaviness and continual sorrow
in his heart for them, why?
For I could wish that myself were accursed from Christ
for my brethren, my kinsmen, according to the flesh.
Brethren, in chapter 10 of the book of Romans,
he says my heart's desire and prayer to God for Israel
is that they might be saved,
but as much as I would want for any person to be saved,
it's a personal decision on a particular day.
We have three children, most of you know that.
We prayed for our children to trust Christ
as their personal savior,
and it was a personal decision on a particular day.
I could not get saved for Julianna, Brianna, or Joseph.
I could not get saved for them,
but I could pray that they would get saved,
and I'm thankful to be able to report this morning
that all three of our children trust at Christ
as their personal savior.
We have, thank God, two grandchildren right now,
a third one on the way in January,
and those two grandchildren, Nova and Bellamy,
you know what I pray, Mark, for them daily,
that they'd be saved,
but you know what I can't do for them?
I can't get saved for them.
Nova's gonna be three in just a few weeks.
She doesn't fully understand,
but she'll say to us often when we're FaceTiming,
because they live in Hawaii,
and she was trying to make me cry last night,
Papa, can you come to my birthday party?
And I said, honey, I can't.
She said, Papa, please.
Man, if you're not a grandfather,
you don't know what that does to your heart,
but she lives in Hawaii.
I can't just jump in a car
and get over there for her birthday,
but she says, can you read me a story about God?
Can you read me a story about Jesus?
That thrills me,
but you know, she's gonna come to a point in her life,
I don't know what the age is gonna be,
but there needs to be a personal decision
on a particular day for Nova Kinsley Mann.
She needs to be saved.
I can't do it for her.
So what am I saying this morning?
Have you been saved?
Have you trusted Jesus Christ as your personal savior?
Could you say this morning
that there was a personal decision on a particular day?
Someone said it this way, God only has children,
he has no grandchildren.
What does he mean by that?
Well, every single person has to trust Christ personally.
The Bible says in John chapter one,
that he came to his own and his own received him not,
but to as many as received him,
to them gave he power to become the sons of God,
even to them that believe on his name.
Can I tell you this morning that God loves you
and he died for you and he rose again,
he conquered sin, death and the grave.
He paid everything that had to be paid
so that you could go to heaven.
He said it this way on the cross, it is finished.
He didn't say it is started
and then you go ahead and take it and finish.
No, he said it is finished.
And he offers to us salvation, a free gift, eternal life.
The question this morning is, have you received it?
Has there been that day,
personal decision on a particular day?
This morning, if you cannot say with certainty
that I know for sure that heaven is my home,
can I tell you what it says in second Corinthians six,
today is the day of salvation.
Today is the day of salvation.
Don't delay, don't leave here without knowing for sure
that heaven is your home.
It would thrill my heart, it would thrill our hearts
for you to trust Christ as your savior today.
But for a moment, could I speak to the people
that are saved?
To those of us that would say,
hey, I've made that personal decision
on that particular day.
I recall just like pastor, you said tomorrow's 29 years.
I remember X number of years ago
when I trust that Christ is my savior, I rejoice with you.
I wonder this morning, are we living for him
who died for us?
Second Corinthians chapter five, verse 17,
I mentioned a few moments ago,
but verse number 15 says that he died for all
that they which live should not henceforth
live unto themselves, but unto him which loved them
and gave himself for them.
Listen, this morning we're to live for Jesus.
We sing the hymn living for Jesus.
I'm gonna live with him for all of eternity
if I'm saved, amen.
If you're saved this morning, you're gonna live with him
for all of eternity.
The question really is this, will you live for him today?
Will you live for him today?
Will you tell others about Jesus and about his love for them
and about what he did on Calvary's cross?
Because the message of salvation is the message
that the world needs.
It's a message that's been entrusted to us
as the people of God to go into all the world
and preach the gospel to every creature
because it is absolutely the hope of humanity.
I was reminded this morning early in my office,
I don't know if you've seen,
I've seen some of the footage, horrific footage
of that flooding situation in Nepal and China.
Just absolutely blows my mind.
The devastation, the quickness of all of that happening
in just a moment.
And I just wonder this morning if there were maybe some
that were giving some type of warning
to get out, to escape.
You know, the issue is this, that warning can go unheeded.
There was, it was not raining.
If you looked at it and understood what happened,
it wasn't raining and all this kind of thing.
What do you mean?
Do you remember Noah?
Hey, there's a flood coming and he preached for 120 years.
And what'd they say?
They mocked him.
Listen, this morning, as believers,
our job is to preach the gospel,
is to preach the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ.
This day is salvation come to this house.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you for the privilege
of being able to gather here this morning.
And God, I pray that you would help us to be responsive.
Lord, that you'd help us to be doers of the word.
God, if there's someone here this morning
that's never trusted the Lord Jesus Christ
as their personal savior,
God, I pray that today they would come
to this old fashioned altar in just a moment
and allow us to take a Bible and show them
how they could know for sure that heaven is their home.
God, I pray that you would help those
that are here that are saved.
Those that have trusted the Lord Jesus Christ,
there was that personal decision on that particular day.
Would you help each one, Lord,
to have a boldness to go forth
and to preach the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ.
Give us a burden, Lord, to share the gospel.
I pray that, Lord, you would have your will and way.
I pray that you would be glorified.
In Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
In just a moment, Kimberly's gonna play the piano,
but before she does, just a word of instruction.
What do we do at this point of our service?
We have what we call an invitation.
And what are we doing?
We're simply inviting you to respond.
We've preached the word of God this morning
and now the opportunity is for you as a hearer
to respond to what you've heard from God's word.
Maybe you're here this morning and you're not sure of heaven.
You would say, preacher, there's never been
that personal decision on that particular day,
but I need to get that settled.
I don't know for sure that I'm going to go to heaven
when I die, but I wanna know.
If you'd come when the piano starts playing,
Mark is here, he'll take a Bible and show you,
I can know for sure that heaven is your home.
If there's a lady that comes, we'll have a lady meet
with you and tell you, I can know for sure
that heaven is your home.
We would not want one single person to leave here
this morning without knowing for sure
that heaven is their home.
Christian, maybe God's put somebody on your heart
that you need to share the gospel with.
Maybe it's a relative, maybe it's a co-worker,
maybe it's a neighbor.
Maybe you need to come and pray and ask the Lord
to give you that boldness and that burden
to take the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ
to that individual.
As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.
Make haste, as Jesus said to Zacchaeus,